Guide to the Vincent Price Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Vincent Price papers
1890-1990
MS 1625
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.33
(19 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, memorabilia, working scripts, writings, photographs, and published material relating to Vincent Price's acting career and activities as a supporter of the visual arts.
Price, Vincent, 1911-1993
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Vincent Price, 1992, and transferred from the Yale Film Studies Center, 1992 and 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiotape, videotape, and motion picture films, as well as preservation masters and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers needing to consult the original materials should refer to the finding aid and/or a reference archivist to determine policies governing reproduction for access.
Biographical / Historical
Vincent Price was born in St. Louis, Missouri, on May 27, 1911. His father was president of the National Candy Company in St. Louis. Price received a B.A. in art history and English from Yale University in 1933, and studied art history at the University of London from 1934 to 1935. Price began his acting career in 1935 in a London stage production of Victoria Regina. He acted in Mercury Theatre productions (1937-1938), in Outward Bound (1939-1940), and in Angel Street (1941-1942). Price made his film debut in 1938 in Service de Luxe. He appeared in over one hundred films, achieving fame particularly in films of horror and suspense. In addition to his stage and film roles, Price performed on radio and television; authored several books; lectured on primitive and modern art; and served on committees and boards of arts organizations, including the Archives of American Art, U.S. Indian Arts and Crafts Board, the arts council of the University of California at Los Angeles, and the White House Fine Arts Commission. Price married three times: to Edith Barrett, Mary Grant, and Coral Browne. He had a son, Vincent Barrett Price, from his first marriage and a daughter, Victoria Price, from his second marriage. Price died in Los Angeles, California, on October 25, 1993.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, memorabilia, working scripts, writings, photographs, and published material relating to Vincent Price's acting career and activities as a supporter of the visual arts.
The bulk ofthe collection dates from the 1940s to the 1970s, although the scrapbooks contain a great deal of material from the 1930s as well. The papers are perhaps most valuable for the ephemera they contain relating to Price's theatrical and film career. There are rare fan magazines and a number of formal and informal photographs documenting all aspects of Price's career. There is also a large amount of material that provides background information on Vincent Price's public life, including scrapbooks, clippings from newspapers and magazines, and reviews of Price's performances. In addition there is good documentation on Price's interest in and involvement with the art world.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in seven series and one addition: I. Correspondence, 1920s-1980s. II. Memorabilia, 1936-1980s. III. Publicity, 1950s-1980s. IV. Working Scripts, 1935-1990, n.d. V. Writings, 1932-1981, n.d. VI. Scrapbooks, 1910-1970s. VII. Photographs, 1890s-1980s.
Actors -- United States; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Motion picture actors and actresses -- United States; Motion pictures; Theater; Price, Vincent, 1911-1993; Price family; United States. Indian Arts and Crafts Board; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1933
- Correspondence, 1920s-1980s; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged alphabetically and primarily consists of incoming letters to Price from relatives, friends, and professional colleagues. Some of the files also include clippings and memorabilia. There are many letters from Price's friend Mildred Mary Combs, playwright Laurence Housman, and various family members, especially Price's parents and his son, Vicent Barrett Price. While Price's professional film and theater career is not well documented in the correspondence, there is material from his agent W. C. Leigh and his publisher Doubleday, as well as personal correspondence with many stage and screen personalities, including Jose Ferrer, Basil Rathbone, and Helen Hayes. Price's involvement in the art world is well documented in correspondence with various artists, particularly Howard Warshaw. There are also many documents pertaining to the founding of the Los Angeles County Art Museum, and correspondence with various art dealers and museum officials. Of interest are the correspondence, office memoranda, and other materials from Price's tenure on the Indian Arts and Crafts Board of the United States Department of the Interior, which detail the Board's activities from 1957 to 1961. Additionally, some correspondence can be found in the working scripts in Series IV: Working Scripts and the pages ofthe scrapbooks in Series VI.
  - A, 1940s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B, 1940s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barrett, Edith, 1935-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - C, 1930s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Combs, Mildred Mary [includes correspondence, clippings and other miscellaneous material], 1940, 1951-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - D, 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Doubleday & Co., Inc., 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - E, 19308-1980s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - F, 19308-1960s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fenton, Mrs. F. Reed ["Hat"; Vincent Price's sister], 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Foster Parents Plan, 1960-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - G, 1930s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gay, Mrs. Samuel T. ["Lallie"; Vincent Prices's sister], 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Grant, Mrs. [Vincent Price's second mother-in-law], 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - H, 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hayes, Helen, 1938-1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - House ofthe Six Directions, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Housman, Laurence, 1935-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - I-J, 1930s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Indian Arts and Crafts Board
    General note
    See folders 51-55
  - K, 1960s-1980s, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - L, 1930s-1960s, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Leigh, W. Colston, Inc. [Vincent Price's agent], 1957-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Los Angeles County Museum, 1947, 1958-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
  - Ma-Mi, 1930s-1980s, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Mo-Mu, 1950s-1960s, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Maitland Collection, 1956-1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - N-O, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Ohio Wesleyan University, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - P, 1940s-1960s, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Perlin, Bernard, 1938-1940, 1948, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Price, J. Mortimer [Vincent Price's brother], 1948-1950, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Price,Mary [Vincent Price's sister-in-law], 1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Price, Mary Grant [Vincent Price's second wife], 1948-1954 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Price, Vincent Jr., 1961 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Price, Vincent Sr. [Mr. and Mrs.], 1927-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 38-40)
  - Price, Vincent Barrett [Vincent Price's son], 1952, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 41-42)
  - R, 1930s-1980s, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Rathbone, Perry T., 1949-1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Sa-Se, 1940s-1960s, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Sh-Sw, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - St. Louis Country Day School, 1926-1928 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - T, 1930s-1980s, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Thomas, Edmond G., 1938, 1951-1960 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - U-V, 1930s-1980s, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - United States. Department of the Interior. Indian Arts and Crafts Board, 1935, 1955-1962, undated (Box 4, Folder 51-55)
  - Vaesen, Guy, 1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 56-57)
  - W, 1950s-1960s, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Warshaw, Helen and Howard, 1945-1951, undated (Box 4, Folder 59-60)
  - Y-Z, 1930s-1960s, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Yale University, 1926-1934, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Unidentified surname
    - A-B, 1940s-1960s, undated (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - C, 1920s-1980s, undated (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - D-G, 1930-1950s, undated (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - H, 1930s-1950s, undated (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - I-J, 1950s-1980s, undated (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - K-L, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - M-O, 1940s-1980s, undated (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - P-R, 1930s-1980s, undated (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - S-Y, 1930s-1960s, undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Unidentified, 1930s-1980s, undated (Box 5, Folder 72)
- Memorabilia, 1936-1980s; Series II
  Most of the materials in this series derive from Price's professional acting career on stage and screen, and include film festival programs, promotional materials for films and the one-man show Diversions and Delights, theater programs, and materials from public performances by or in honor of Price. Also included are some awards and certificates as well as materials from two advertising campaigns for consumer products on which Price worked. The items in this series are arranged by type. More memorabilia, especially pertaining to theater productions, can be found in Series VI: Scrapbooks.
  - Advertising, 1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Awards and certificates, 1948-1969, 1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 74-76)
  - Biography of Coral Browne, undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Programs
    - Film, 1981, 1984, undated (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Readings, tributes, and lectures, 1939, 1971-1976, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Theater, 1936, 1942, 1955, 1975-1979 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Promotional materials
    - Film, 1962, 1970, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Theater, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - Script Concept, undated (Box 5, Folder 83)
- Publicity, 1950s-1980s; Series III
  This series is divided into two sections: Clippings and Publications. The Clippings section, arranged alphabetically by subject, consists of excerpts from mostly United States newspapers and magazines, and ranges in date from the 1960s to the 1980s. This section provides a good overview of Vincent Price's public life. For basic biographical information about Vincent Price, the "General" and "Profiles and Interviews" folders are good resources. Theater reviews are well represented, especially for Diversions and Delights, Price's one-man show about Oscar Wilde. Price's career on the lecture circuit is documented in the "Art," "Lectures," and "Villains Still Pursue Me" folders. Other clippings pertaining to his acting career and his family can be found in Series VI: Scrapbooks. The Publications section dates from the 1950s to the 1980s and is arranged alphabetically by type. The section contains movie fan magazines, privately produced fanzines, catalogs of Price's art exhibits, and books and publications about Price's film career.
  - Clippings, 1960s-1980s
    - Art [price's exhibit; reviews ofart talks; article by Price on museums] (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Diversions and Delights [reviews, advertisements, promotional materials] (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Family (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Films of Vincent Price [articles, interviews, reviews, publicity] (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - General [community activities, honors] (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - I Like What I Know [reviews and excerpt from Price's autobiography] (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Lectures by Vincent Price [reviews and excerpts] (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Profiles and interviews ofVincent Price (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Television [reviews and publicity] (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - Theater [reviews] (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - The Villains Still Pursue Me [lecture series; publicity and reviews] (Box 6, Folder 94)
    - Walker Art Center, Minneapolis, Minnesota [magazine, calendars, review] (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Publications
    - Books
      - The Films of Vincent Price by lain F. McAsh, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 96)
      - Heroes of the Movies: Vincent Price by lain F. McAsh, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 97)
      - Vincent Price: Actor and Art Collector by Raul Lopez and Alan Curl, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 98)
    - Catalogs
      - American International Pictures: Twenty-five Years [catalog for retrospective], 1979 (Box 6, Folder 99)
      - Vincent Price Collects Drawings [catalog for exhibition; foreword and notes by Price], 1957 September (Box 6, Folder 100)
    - Independent fanzines
      - II Falcone Maltese N.3 [in Italian; Price interview and filmography], 1974 September (Box 6, Folder 101)
      - Hollywood Excitement Book One, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 102)
      - The Skull No.2: Vincent Price [in French; extensive Price filmography], 1973 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - Magazines
      - L'ecran Fantastique [nos. 15, 17, 18], 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 104)
      - Famous Monsters [nos. 14,19,109,149,158], 1961-1980 (Box 7, Folder 105)
      - Films and Filming, 1968 November (Box 7, Folder 106)
      - Monsterland, 1985 April (Box 7, Folder 107)
      - Movie Life, 1964 April (Box 7, Folder 108)
      - Photoplay, 1969 October (Box 7, Folder 109)
- Working scripts, 1935-1990; Series IV
  This series consists ofthe working scripts, many annotated and autographed, used by Vincent Price for his performances on radio, television, stage, and screen, and in the recording studio. The scripts are arranged by title within each category ofperformance.
  - Film
    - Edward Scissorhands [screenplay by CarolineThompson; letter], 1990 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Television and Radio
    - Famous Ghost Stories [radio production] (Box 8, Folder 111)
    - Five Chelsea Lane: A Victorian Thriller in Three Acts [play by Patrick Hamilton; adapted for radio], 1939 (Box 8, Folder 112)
    - KPFA-FM [promotional announcements] (Box 8, Folder 113)
    - Tales of Extrasensory Perception [radio production], 1958 (Box 8, Folder 114)
  - Theater
    - Angel Street [by Patrick Hamilton], 1952 (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - Charley's Aunt [by Brandon Price; two annotated copies, one belonging to Vincent Price, one to his wife Coral Browne], ca. 1962 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - The Cocktail Party [by T. S. Eliot], Circa 1951 (Box 8, Folder 117)
    - Dial M For Murder [by Frederick Knott], 1956 (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Don Juan in Hell [by George Bernard Shaw; two bound copies with annotations, and a script for the First Drama Quartet, with enclosed correspondence regarding the production], 1952 (Box 9, Folder 119-121)
    - Elizabeth the Queen [by Maxwell Anderson] (Box 9, Folder 122)
    - Goodbye Again: A New Play [by Allan Scott and George Haight; with enclosures], 1952 (Box 9, Folder 123)
    - The Lady's Not for Burning [by Christopher Fry], 1952 (Box 9, Folder 124)
    - Outward Bound [by Sutton Vane], 1939 (Box 9, Folder 125)
    - 27 Wagons Full of Cotton and Other Plays [by Tennessee Williams] (Box 9, Folder 126)
    - Victoria Regina [by Lawrence Housman], 1935 (Box 10, Folder 127)
    - Visit to a Small Planet [by Gore Vidal; with enclosures], 1958 (Box 10, Folder 128)
  - Other
    - America the Beautiful [dramatic readings of American poetry and songs] (Box 10, Folder 129)
    - The Butterfly Ball and the Grasshopper's Feast [written by Alan Aldridge and William Plomer; inscribed Vincent Price Royal Albert Hall Oct 16th 1975" and "Music Roger Glover;" some reading directions and editions; names in back leaf] (Box 10, Folder 130)
    - D. H. Lawrence and the Women in Love [written by Guy Vaesen] (Box 10, Folder 131)
    - If I Forget Thee [written by Ben Aronin; typescript of dramatic reading at the Jerusalem Anniversary Dinner], 1954 (Box 10, Folder 132)
    - Poetry [Longfellow, Poe, Shakespeare] (Box 10, Folder 133)
- Writings, 1932-1981; Series V
  This series is arranged by type, and consists ofthe plays, poetry, and other writings of Vincent Price. His early efforts at play writing are represented by manuscripts of Poet's Corner and Those Enduring Young Charms. There is also a manuscript for The Book of Joe, a memoir of his beloved dog's life.
  - Articles
    - "The Baltimore I Love", 1981 (Box 10, Folder 134)
  - Books
    - The Book of Joe [typescript] (Box 10, Folder 135-136)
  - Lectures and speeches
    - American life lecture (Box 10, Folder 137)
    - American literature lecture and Tennessee Williams reading (Box 10, Folder 138)
    - Art lecture [City College, New York] (Box 10, Folder 139)
    - "Club Women Are No Laughing Matter" [California] (Box 10, Folder 140)
    - "The Enjoyment of Art" [lecture at Brigham Young University], 1959 (Box 10, Folder 141)
    - Gaugin lecture (Box 10, Folder 142)
    - "McKnight Humanities Foundation" [Macalester College], 1960 April 19 (Box 10, Folder 143)
    - Museum dedication [California] (Box 10, Folder 144)
    - Untitled
      - Boston, Circa 1946 (Box 10, Folder 145)
      - Chicago, Circa 1946 (Box 10, Folder 146)
  - Plays
  - Poets Corner: A Play in Three Acts [written manuscripts and typescripts] (Box 11, Folder 147-148)
  - Those Enduring Young Charms [written manuscript] (Box 11, Folder 149)
  - Poetry, 1932, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 150)
  - Other
    - Art labels [catalog descriptions written by Price] (Box 11, Folder 151)
    - Notes on art (Box 11, Folder 152)
- Scrapbooks, 1910s-1970s; Series VI
  This series consists of Vincent Price's scrapbooks, containing news clippings, programs, invitations, letters, and photographs, and is divided into two sections, Theater and Other. Some of the scrapbooks were disassembled for preservation purposes. Separated material is now stored in folders with each volume. Price's theater career is well documented here, especially his appearances in Victoria Regina and Diversions andDelights. There is also genealogical and biographical :material for the Price family. Similar materials can be found in Series II: Memorabilia and in the "Clippings" section of Series III: Publicity.
  - Theater scrapbooks
    - Angel Street [clippings, programs], 1941-1942, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 153)
    - Diversions and Delights, 1977-1978
      - Scrapbook (Box 14)
      - Enclosures [newspaper clippings] (Box 11, Folder 154)
    - "New York Stage I" [clippings programs for The Lady Has a Heart and Mercury ], 1937-1938 (Box 11, Folder 155)
    - "New York Stage II" [clippings programs for Mambia 's Daughters and Outward Bound ], 1938-1941 (Box 12, Folder 156)
    - Victoria Regina
      - Clippings, programs, correspondence, 1935-1940 (Box 12, Folder 157)
      - Newspaper clippings scrapbook, 1930s (Box 12, Folder 158)
      - Wooden scrapbook, 1935-1936 (Box 14)
      - Enclosures from wooden scrapbook [newspaper clippings]
        - About Vincent Price (Box 12, Folder 159)
        - Films of Vincent Price (Box 12, Folder 160)
        - Photograph of Vincent Price (Box 12, Folder 161)
        - Theater performances of Vincent Price (Box 12, Folder 162)
  - Other scrapbooks
    - Art exhibit [photographs with captions by Price] (Box 13, Folder 163-164)
    - Mike Douglas Show, 1967
      - Album cover with annotations and autographs (Box 13, Folder 165)
      - Photographs (Box 13, Folder 166)
    - Family and early career scrapbook [contains Price family correspondence; clippings; and theater memorabilia], 1910s-1930s (Box 13, Folder 167)
    - Later career scrapbook [clippings, programs], 1936-1962 (Box 13, Folder 168)
- Photographs, 1890s-1980s; Series VII
  The Photographs series consists ofphotographs pertaining to Vincent Price's family, professional career, art collecting, and personal life. This collection of images sheds light on Price's personality and range of interests. The series has been divided into three sections: Vincent Price, Other individuals, and Oversize. Oversize pictures are arranged in the same order as the first two sections.
  The Vincent Price section is arranged in several categories: Art collection; Portraits; Candids; Film; Interviews, speeches, public appearances; Radio; Television; and Theater. The "Portraits" files include formal posed photographs ofPrice, many made for promotional purposes as Price pursued his acting career. "Candids" are informal photographs showing Price's lighter, more casual side. The other categories document Price's work in various productions. Price's "Film" work is represented by promotional shots and film stills. Those films with an extensive number of pictures include The Abominable Dr. Phibes, House of Usher, and The Long Night. The "Theater" folders do not cover as wide a spectrum of productions as do those for his films, but they do detail Price's performances in Oliver!, Diversions and Delights, Victoria Regina, and Shoemaker's Holiday. Some examples of Price's work in other media are included in the "Radio" and "Television" folders.
  The Other individuals section includes photographs of Price's first and third wives, Edith Barrett and Coral Browne, and of several generations ofthe Price family of St. Louis. The "Price Family" folders feature pictures of all sizes, ages, and subjects--from cartes de visite of Price ancestors to color prints ofPrice's daughter, Mary Victoria. There are a number of images that document Price's childhood in St. Louis and his student days at Yale. Also in this series are several pictures ofPrice's colleagues in film and the theater.
  - Price, Vincent
    - Art collection
      - Art (Box 15, Folder 169-172)
      - Vincent Price with art (Box 15, Folder 173)
      - Drawings
        See: Folder 201
    - Portraits
      - General (Box 15, Folder 174-176)
        General
        See also: Folders 202-203
      - Books [I Like What I Know]
        See: Folder 204
      - Film (Box 15, Folder 177)
        See also: Folder 205
      - Theatre (Box 15, Folder 178)
    - Candids
      - General (Box 15, Folder 179)
        See also: Folders 206-207
      - Film festivals (Box 15, Folder 180)
      - Look shoot (Box 15, Folder 181)
      - Price on vacation (Box 15, Folder 183)
    - Film
      - General (Box 15, Folder 184-186)
      - Lobby cards
        See: Folder 208
      - The Abominable Dr. Phibes
        See: Folders 209-210
      - House of Usher (Box 16, Folder 187)
      - The Long Night (Box 16, Folder 188)
      - Price cooking (Box 15, Folder 182)
    - Interviews, Speeches, Public Appearances (Box 16, Folder 189)
    - Radio (Box 16, Folder 190)
    - Television (Box 15, Folder 191)
      See also: Folder 211
    - Theater
      - General (Box 16, Folder 192)
      - Diversions and Delights (Box 16, Folder 193)
      - The Lady Has a Heart
        See: Folder 212
      - Oliver! (Box 16, Folder 194)
      - Richard III
        See: Folder 213
      - Shoemaker's Holiday
        See: Folder 214
      - Victoria Regina (Box 16, Folder 195)
  - Other individuals
    - Barrett, Edith (Box 16, Folder 196)
    - Barrett, Edith and Vincent Price (Box 16, Folder 197)
    - Browne, Coral (Box 16, Folder 198)
      See also: Folder 215
    - Price family (Box 16, Folder 199)
      See also: Folder 216
    - Miscellaneous (Box 16, Folder 200)
      See also: Folder 217
  - Oversize
    - Price, Vincent
      - Art collection
        - Drawings (Box 17, Folder 201)
      - Portraits
        - General (Box 17, Folder 202-203)
          See also: Folders 174-176
        - Books [ I Like What I Know ] (Box 17, Folder 204)
        - Film (Box 17, Folder 205)
          See also: Folder 177
      - Candids
        - General (Box 17, Folder 206-207)
          See also: Folder 179
      - Film
        - Lobby cards (Box 18, Folder 208)
        - The Abominable Dr. Phibes (Box 18, Folder 209-210)
      - Television (Box 18, Folder 211)
        See also: Folder 191
      - Theater
        - The Lady Has a Heart (Box 18, Folder 212)
        - Richard III (Box 18, Folder 213)
        - Shoemaker's Holiday (Box 18, Folder 214)
    - Other individuals
      - Browne, Coral (Box 18, Folder 215)